A Guide to the Milka Bliznakov Prize Records, 1999-2012, 2016
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Milka Bliznakov Prize Records, 1999-2012, 2016
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms2001-045
1 box; 0.5 cu. ft.
The Milka Bliznakov Prize, established in 1998, honors the founder of the International Archive of Women in Architecture. The prize is conferred in recognition of research that advances knowledge of women's contributions to architecture and related design fields, and was created to encourage the use and growth of the International Archive of Women in Architecture (IAWA). The collection consists of announcements about the award, proposal submissions for the prize, and original works of research.
International Archive of Women in Architecture (IAWA)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
The Milka Bliznakov Prize Records were donated to the International Archive of Women in Architecture at the Special Collections. Accruals are ongoing.
Historical Information
The Milka Bliznakov Prize, established in 1998, is named in honor of the founder of the International Archive of Women in Architecture, architect and Virginia Tech Professor Emerita Milka Bliznakov. The prize is conferred in recognition of research that advances knowledge of women's contributions to architecture and related design fields, and was created to encourage the use and growth of the IAWA. The prize winner is determined in a two stage process. In Stage One, applicants register their proposal, which outlines the work they plan to complete within the coming year. Stage Two occurs the following year, when applicants submit their completed projects. The winner of the prize is selected from among these projects.
In 2011, for the 11th Annual Prize, the prize committee altered the guidelines to include the stipulation that a portion of the research for the project must use IAWA collections and renamed the award The Milka Bliznakov Research Prize. The awarding of the prize still occurs in a two stage process. In Stage One, applicants submit their proposal, which outlines the research they plan to conduct at the IAWA, a proposed schedule for residency to include a open presentation on their research, and a description of the product they plan to produce (e.g. research paper, book, visual or physical original work). The winner of the prize is selected from among these proposals. In stage two, the Prize winner conducts their research at the IAWA and submits their project for inclusion in the IAWA collections by December of that year.
Milka Bliznakov Award and Research Prize Winners
2001, Claire Bonney, The Work and Life of Adrienne Gorska.
2002, Elizabeth Birmingham, Searching for Marion Mahony: Gender, Erasure, and the Discourse of Architectural Studies.
2003, Barbara Nadel,Security Design: Achieving Transparency in Civic Architecture
2003, Ozlem Erkarslan, Turkish Women Architects in the Late Ottoman and Early Republican Era 1908-1960.
2004, Dorrita Hannah, un-housing performance: The Heart of PQ
2004, Janet Stoyel, Sonicloth.
2005, Carmen Alonso Espegel, Heroines of the Space
2005, Isabel Bauer, Architekturstudentinnen der Weimarer Republik
2005, Bobbye Tigerman, 'I Am Not a Decorator' Florence Knoll, the Knoll Planning Unit, and the Making of the Modern Office.
2005, Milka Bliznakov Honorarium, Joseph Chuo Wang.
2006, Milka Bliznakov Prize, Commendation, Eran Ben-Joseph, Holly D. Ben-Joseph and Anne C. Dodge Against All Odds: MIT's Pioneering Women of Landscape Architecture
2007, No prize awarded.
2008, Martha Alonso, Sonia Bevilacqua, and Graciela Brandariz, Odilia Suárez: The Exemplary Trajectory of an Architect and Urbanist in Latin America
2008, Despina Stratigakos, A Woman’s Berlin.
2008, Milka Bliznakov Prize, Commendation, Lori Brown, feminist practices [exhibition].
2009, Patrick Lee Lucas, Sarah Hunter Kelly: Designing the House of Good Taste.
2010, Inge Schaefer Horton, Early Women Architects of the San Francisco Bay Area.
2011, Lindsay Nencheck, Organizing Voices: Examining the 1974 Women in Architecture Symposium at Washington University in St. Louis.
2012, Andrea J. Merrett, Feminism in American Architecture: Organizing 1972-1975.
2016, Ines Moisset, Florencia Marciani, Silvina Barraud, Cecilia Kesman, Beatriz Ojeda, and Marcela Roitman, Women Architects on the Web
Scope and Content
The collection consists of yearly information and announcements about the Milka Bliznakov Prize and research proposal submissions. This prize is awarded annually and more records are expected at a later date.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged chronologically by year of submission. Information is divided into award announcements, which advertise the award and announce winners at various stages, proposal submissions, and original works of research.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
Additional information about the Milka Bliznakov Prize is available through links on the IAWA home page.
The IAWA Records, Ms1985-021, and the papers of Milka Bliznakov, Ms1991-025, are both housed with the IAWA and are on the IAWA Guide to the Collections.
Index Terms
Persons:
Alonso, Carmen Espegel; Alonso, Martha; Barraud, Silvina; Bauer, Isabel; Ben-Joseph, Eran; Ben-Joseph, Holly D.; Bevilacqua, Sonia; Birmingham, Elizabeth J.; Bliznakov, Milka T., d. 2010; Bonney, Claire; Brandariz, Graciela; Brown, Lori; Dodge, Anne C.; Erkarslam, Ozlem; Hannah, Dorrita; Horton, Inge S.; Kesman, Cecilia; Lucas, Patrick Lee; Merrett, Andrea J.; Marciani, Florencia; Moisset, Ines; Nadel, Barbara; Ojeda, Beatriz; Roitman, Marcela; Stoyel, Janet; Stratigakus, Despina; Tigerman, Bobbye; Wang, Joseph Chuo
Subjects:
International Archive of Women in Architecture (IAWA); Milka Bliznakov Prize
Contents List
- First Milka Blizankov Prize, 1999-2000
  - Award Announcements (Box-folder 1:1)
  - Proposal Submissions (Box-folder 1:2)
    - Information Exchange and Knowledge Transfer among Female Architects by Cordula Mohr
    - The Quintessential Colter: Mary Jane Colter and the Development of Organic American Architecture by Kweku Quansa
  - Winning proposal (Box-folder 1:3)
    - Adrienne Gorska by Claire Bonney see also Claire Bonney Architectural Papers, 1995-1998, 2002
- Second Milka Blizankov Prize, 2001-2002
  - Award Announcements (Box-folder 1:4)
  - Proposal Submissions (Box-folder 1:5)
    - On Gertrude Sawyer by Judith H. Lanius
    - Searching for Marion Mahony: Gender, Erasure, and the Discourse of Architectural Studies by Dr. Elizabeth Cunningham [Prize Winner]
    - Making Deeper Connections: Women in Architecture by Neeti Gupta
    - Where are the Women in Landscape Architecture? A Proposal to Find Out by Terry Clements
    - Mentors and Students: Building the Community of Female Architects by Dr. Catherine Zipf
    - La Casa di Eva by Dr. Maristella Casciato
    - The Architecture and Urbanism Between the X-Urban/Industrial/Wired Condition by Lora H. Kim
    - Contemporary Female Dutch Architects Compared to their Japanese Counterparts by Tina Lin
    - The Houses of Lisl Scheu Close by Jane King Hession
    - Curriculum vitae of Mr. Wei Chen
    - Women and Design by Marta Zarza
    - Handbook and CD to Strengthen the Participation of Community Groups in Urban Renewal Projects by Dr. Ombretta Romice
    - Cultural Politics and Historiography: Mapping Feminist Writing on Canadian and American Architecture by Sarah Bassnett
  - Winner's curriculum vitae (Box-folder 1:6)
    - Dr. Elizabeth Birmingham
- Third Milka Blizankov Prize, 2002-2003
  - Award Announcements (Box-folder 1:7)
  - Proposal Submissions, part 1 (Box-folder 1:8)
    - The Application of Game Theory to the Field of Architecture by Alissa Luepke
    - Lina Bo Bardi's Museum Picture Gallery: Research through Drawings and Paintings by Bo Bardi by Cathrine Veikos
    - Florence Knoll Bassett and the Design of New York International Airport by David Brodherson
    - The History of Koryn Rolstad's Contributions to Architecture by Lynn Boyle
  - Proposal Submissions, part 2 (Box-folder 1:9)
    - TRANS_it - A Discourse on Temporality and Nomadic Condition by Sofie Redele and Iris Kaltenegger
    - Security Design: Achieving Transparency in Civic Architecture by Barbara A. Nadel [Prize Winner]
    - Design Proposal by Maribel Guerra
    - Turkish Women Architects in the Late Ottoman and Early Republican Era 1908-1960 by Ozlem Erdogdu Erkarslan [Prize Winner]
    - Politics and Gender in the Viennese Architecture of the 1930s: The Case of Helene Koller-Buchweiser by Maria Rentetzi
- Fourth Milka Blizankov Prize, 2003-2004
  - Award Announcements [Prize Winners: Dorrita Hannah and Janet Stoyel] (Box-folder 1:10)
- Fifth Milka Blizankov Prize, 2004-2005
  - Award Announcements [Prize Winners: Carmen Alonso Espegel, Isabel Bauer, and Bobbye Tigerman] (Box-folder 1:11)
- Eleventh Milka Bliznakov Research Prize, 2011
  - Submitted Work, research paper: 'Organizing Voices: Examining the 1974 Women in Architecture Symposium at Washington University in St. Louis,' by Lindsay Nencheck 2011 (Box-folder 1:12)
  - Supporting Documentation:
    - CD, Women in Architecture Symposium, Lynn Meyer's Student Videos, 1974 (Box-folder 1:13)
    - CD, Washington University Women in Architecture Symposium Audio Files, 1974 (Box-folder 1:13)
    - DVD, Alice Franklin Student Video, 1974 (Box-folder 1:13)
- Twelveth Milka Bliznakov Research Prize, 2012
  - Submitted Work, research paper: ''Feminism in American Architecture: Organizing 1972-1975,' by Andrea J. Merrett 2012 (Box-folder 1:14)
- Sixteenth Milka Bliznakov Research Prize, 2016
  - Submitted Work, research paper: 'Women Architects on the Web,' by Ines Moisset, Florencia marciani, Silvina Barraud, Cecilia Kesman, Beatriz Ojeda, and Marcela Roitman, 2016 (Box-folder 1:15)